Liton Chowdhury

Contact Address: C/O, Anwar Hossain, JA- 103/1 (4th Floor), Wireless Gate, Mohakhali, Banani, Dhaka-1212; 101729081907, E-mail: litoon_ctg@yahoo.com



Career Objective

To join in a benign organization and hold a senior position in Supply Chain Management by dedicating all of my effort, skill, experience & ability for the organizational development.

Professional Summary

Having around 16 years professional experience in Supply Chain & Merchandising domains in two Group of companies to ensure effective supply chain management by using 3P approach (Policy-Process-People) and the tools & techniques of operational excellence. Moreover, mentioning the following key sub-domains of Supply Chain in which I always moving around:

- 1. Sourcing 2. Procurement (Local and International)
- 3. Material management 4. Logistics operation (Inbound)

Area of Expertise: Supply Chain drivers management, SC Macro process implementation, Strategic Negotiation, Process Re-engineering, New Business Development, People Management, Supplier Relationship Management, Store Management.

Professional Experience

At Standard Group, Civil Engineers Bhaban, 69, Mohakhali C/A, Dhaka-1212 At Karnaphuli Sportswear Ind. Ltd. in Youngone Group (BD), CEPZ, Chattogram

STANDARD GROUP

Standard Group is one of the leading garment manufacturers in Bangladesh. This group incorporated as one of the country's pioneer garments manufacturer and exporter specialized in woven area-products: outer wear, top and bottom item, also it has an operation in knit area-products: sweater, pullover item etc. This group is growing up by 394 production lines where more than 55K people are working to accomplish 6 million pieces monthly production capacity which catch to around \$425 million yearly turnover. Its customer base ranges from small retailers to large hyper-marts who are situated in North America, Europe and Asia region. Now, almost 20 retailers are staying in this group where Gap, AEO, A&F, Tommy Hilfiger, M&S, George, Lands' End, TCP, Carhartt, J.Crew etc. captured major portion.

Sourcing Manager; Grade-5 (Role as a Head of Sourcing): 01 December 2017 to 31 December 2019 **Assistant Sourcing Manager**: 01 June 2013 to November 2017

Major Responsibilities:

- Assisted the team with an efficient and effective way to attain targets.
- Planed, developed and implemented of strategy for sourcing and procurement.
- Identified areas for process improvement and system enhancement.
- Analyzed market and delivery systems in order to assess present and future material availability.
- Identified creative ways to reduce cost by streamlining processes and systems (i.e. modification of responsibilities or consolidation of tasks, elimination of non-value-added processes or complete reengineering of processes and systems).
- Business development.
- Managed the different aspects of supply chain activities including sourcing, purchasing, logistic etc.
- Evaluated quality, pricing, delivery schedules, payment process and determine the best products and suppliers.
- Sourced different brand, quality, and suppliers according to buyer's requirements.
- Build up a strong relationship in between suppliers and merchandisers.

- Maintained association with accounts & finance, commercial, customs bond, logistic and other manufacturing & operational teams for smooth working.
- Forecasted price trends and its impact on future activities.
- Make sure that the required product is purchased in right time, accurate quality with competitive price.
- Arranged vendor survey in order to check a) order history b) financial strength of vendors
 c) Market reputation d) compliance etc.

Key Achievements:

- 1. Select Shipping Term: During each and every overseas shipment, we have been started to cross-check freight charge through to our logistic department then do compare with supplier's demand on freight charge to keep same transit lead time. As a result, we are able to move by around 80% shipments on FOB basis i/o CFR Ctg. where we get supply chain efficiency by freight cost savings.
- 2. Select Payment Term: During each delivery or shipment, we have been started to collect two prices based on LC at sight and deferred LC or TT payment then we do analysis which one is feasible for us. Once in a quarter, we arrange comparing rate (in between LC terms) from our finance dept. In this way, we able to add extra value which can raise the supply chain profitability.
- 3. Propose Competitive Source: In terms of sole nominated supplier, we have been started to propose competitive source to buyer with keeping same quality. In this way, we got some successes in last couple of years. As an example, we got buyer approval on our counter submission against sole nominated supplier from where we brought fabric last five years as 3 millions yards round the year denim program against TCP (The Children Place, USA). In this way, we able to add extra margin which can raise the supply chain surplus.

YOUNGONE GROUP

Section Leader: November. 2009 to May 2013

Team Leader: August 2006 to October 2009; Merchandising Dept. (Buyer: Polo Ralph Lauren, USA)

Major Responsibilities:

- Scheduled supply chain activities for product development, costing, production follow-up, day-to-day communication with buyers, correct consumption, testing, packaging, purchase plan, place orders and sales forecasts.
- Followed up orders with customers and internal production house to ensure retailer's satisfaction and on-time delivery.
- Submitted sample to customer for approval, arranged appropriate artwork to ensure the bulk order.
- Problem troubleshooting and solved which raised during sample development and bulk production.
- Prepared TNA chart and ensured on-time delivery to hit the TNA plan.
- Worked together with CAD, technicians, Q.A and production concern.
- Prepared WIP and monitored order status in terms of productivity and delivery.
- Followed up with planning/production/commercial team to make sure shipment timely.
- Ensured perpetual and full inventory counts and stock reconciled with Material control department.
- Monitored the movement of raw materials, inventory management and logistics supports.
- Assisted to management in preparing procurement plan and process improvement.
- Found out rejected/damaged quantities and worked with suppliers for replacing of those quantities.
- Collected competitive price from suppliers and prepared competitive statement for management decision.
- Sourced and selected appropriate vendors for materials considering quality, best price and service.
- Maintained updated and detailed database of suppliers.

YOUNGONE GROUP

Team Member- Material Control (Buyer: TNF- The North Face, USA): February 2004 to July 2006

Major Responsibilities:

Handled large number of SKUs and proper storage of all materials.

- Ensured timely replenishment of stock by monitoring the reorder levels.
- Counted & measured GR (Goods Receipt) and controlled all related records in SAP: MM- module.
- Inspected items as quality & quantity and participated physical inventories by counting stock.
- Maintained & updated records of all materials for informing to management.
- Ensured on time material's issue as per production requirements.
- Implemented Safety, Health & Environment regulations as per company policy.

Academic Information

Master of Business Administration (M.B.A)

Major in Management

Result: CGPA- 3.48 out of 4.00

Passing Year: 2003

Institution: University of Chittagong

Bachelor of Business Administration (4-year B.B.A)

Major in Management Result: 2nd class

Passing Year: 2001

Institution: University of Chittagong

Computer Literacy

MS-word, MS-Excel, habitual to work in SAP system, having good knowledge on Internet Browsing.

Languages

Having fluency in both written and spoken English and also well confident in Business Communication.

Internship

I continued at M. M. Ispahani Ltd. by three months as an Intern under my M.B.A program during December'02 to Feb'03 and submitted a market survey report on "Ispahani Tea".

Professional Qualifications

Certified Supply Chain Manager (CSCM)

Certified by ISCEA-USA (International Supply Chain Education Alliance)

Certificate Course on Supply Chain Management

Organized by IBA, Dhaka University

Project Management Competencies for Professionals (PMC)

A six-week course by IBA, Dhaka University

Personal Information

Father's Name : Late Parimol Chowdhury

Mother's Name : Mrs. Priti Kana Chowdhury

Date of Birth : 10th November, 1976

Permanent Address: Vill+P.O.- Kadhurkhil; P.S.-Boalkhali; Dist- Chattogram

References

1) Mohammad Tofazzal Ali

Executive Director Standard Group

Mobile: +88-01711530333; E-mail: ali.t@standard-group.com

2) Md. Rezaul Karim

Human Resource Manager

Standard Group

Mobile: +88-01713257171; E-mail: rezaul.k@standard-group.com